Guide to the Benjamin Lee Smith Papers, 1916-1961, bulk 1930-1961 RL.01210
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Benjamin Lee Smith papers
1916-1961, bulk 1930-1961
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Smith, Benjamin Lee
RL.01210
12.4 Linear Feet
North Carolina educator and superintendent of public schools in Greensboro, N.C. The papers of Benjamin Lee Smith, North Carolina educator and Duke University alumnus, span the years 1916-1961, and contain correspondence, memoranda, clippings, and other printed material related to public education at both the local and state levels in North Carolina. There are also several dozen photographs of N.C. school buildings and personnel, circa 1930s-1950s. Papers are arranged in the following series: Correspondence, Subject Files (the largest series in the collection), Clippings, Printed Material, and Speeches. Other topics include prohibition and the elections of 1928, and religion and politics in North Carolina. A small but significant amount of material concerns school integration in Greensboro and associated civil rights issues in North Carolina (located within boxes 10, 11, 14-16, 21, 24, 26 and 31). Collection also includes material on charitable organizations in which Smith was active, especially the Methodist Church, North Carolina Education Association (NCEA), Kiwanis Club, Boy Scouts, and the Horace Mann League.
9300 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Benjamin Lee Smith Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1961.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1893 Feb. 6 Benjamin Lee Smith born, Granite Falls, Caldwell County, N.C.
1916 A.B., Duke University
1916-1917 Served in U.S. Army
1919-1924 Superintendent of Schools, Forest City (N.C.)
1922-1934 Taught summer school classes for Appalachian State Teachers College, N.C.
1924-1929 Superintendent of Schools, Rutherfordton-Spindale
1925 Served as secretary for the newly chartered Rutherfordton Kiwanis Club
1927-1934 Member of NC Textbook Commission
1929-1934 Superintendent of Schools, Shelby
1935-1958 Superintendent of Schools, Greensboro
1937 M.A., Duke University
1938-1939 President, N.C. Education Association (NCEA)
1949-1950 President, Horace Mann League of the U.S.
1958 Retired from position as N.C. schools superintendent
1959 Participated in National Civil Rights hearing on school integration
1961 Year of death
Collection Overview
The papers of Benjamin Lee Smith, North Carolina educator and Duke University alumnus, span the years 1916-1961, and contain correspondence, memoranda, clippings, and other printed material related to public education at both the local and state levels in North Carolina. There are also several dozen photographs of N.C. school buildings and personnel, circa 1930s-1950s. Papers are arranged in the following series: Correspondence, Subject Files (the largest series in the collection), Clippings, Printed Material, and Speeches. Other topics include prohibition and the elections of 1928, and religion and politics in North Carolina. A small but significant amount of material concerns school integration in Greensboro and associated civil rights issues in North Carolina (located within boxes 10, 11, 14-16, 21, 24, 26 and 31). Collection also includes material on charitable organizations in which Smith was active, especially the Methodist Church, North Carolina Education Association (NCEA), Kiwanis Club, Boy Scouts, and the Horace Mann League.
North Carolina -- Social conditions; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1928; Elections -- North Carolina -- 1928; Educators -- North Carolina -- Correspondence; Civil rights -- North Carolina; African Americans -- Segregation -- North Carolina; School integration -- North Carolina; Public Schools -- North Carolina; Prohibition -- North Carolina; North Carolina -- Race relations; North Carolina -- Politics and government -- 1951-; North Carolina -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950; Greensboro (N.C.) -- History; Smith, Benjamin Lee; Smith, Benjamin Lee; Boy Scouts of America; Kiwanis International; Horace Mann League; Segregation in education -- North Carolina; Methodist Church -- North Carolina
- Correspondence Series, 1935-1961, 4 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Folders house incoming and outgoing correspondence generated over the course of Benjamin Smith's career as an educator. Many letters are routine exchanges such as letters of recommendation, requests for assistance, and invitations to speak. Arranged alphabetically; some letters may have more than one folder of materials. Individuals or topics represented by their own folders include: Dr. George Harley, the Palmer Memorial Institute, Susan Blair Smith, and Personal Correspondence.
  - Folders A-G (Box 1)
  - Folders H-P (Box 2)
  - Folders P-S (Box 3)
  - Folders S-Z (Box 4)
- Subject Files Series, 1916-1961, bulk 1930-1961, 23 boxes
  Houses files assembled by Smith on a variety of topics, chiefly related to associations with which he was involved, or events and activities of personal and professional interest. The largest two groups of files document the career and personal affairs of Benjamin Lee Smith, and selected activities and aspects of the Methodist Church. Other individuals or topics represented by a substantial group of folders include the Boy Scouts of America; the centennial celebration for public education; Duke University; Greensboro Public Schools; integration of schools in N.C.; and the North Carolina Education Association. Materials on the public school system of North Carolina and selected counties can be found scattered throughout the collection, particularly within boxes 10, 11, 14-16, 21, 24, 26 and 31. There is one folder containing several dozen exterior and interior photographs of N.C. public school buildings (most unidentified, but some in Shelby), circa 1930s-1950s, along with shots of school personnel; there are also photographs of Smith (circa 1899, 1916-1917, and circa 1958) included in his personal files. Arranged in alphabetical order as received, with original titles by Smith.
  - American Association of School Librarians, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - American Trails Pioneer Association (Box 5)
  - Appalachian Summer School (Box 5)
  - Architects (Box 5)
  - Aycock Memorial (Box 5)
  - Boy Scouts of America, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Boy Scouts of America, 6 folders (Box 6)
  - Brooks School dedication, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Carolina Charter Tercentenary Commission (Box 7)
  - Centennial celebration of progress in public education in N.C., 8 folders (Box 7)
  - Centennial celebration of progress in public education in N.C., 8 folders (Box 8)
  - Centennial celebration of progress in public education in N.C., 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Character education, courtesy, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Christians and Jews, National Conference, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Children (Box 9)
  - Church (Box 9)
  - Citizen Award and retirement letters, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Commission on Civil Rights (Box 10)
    [Contains material on integration]
  - Conferences, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Daniels, Josephus (Box 10)
  - Declamations, debates (Box 10)
  - Desegregation, 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Distribution of state funds (Box 11)
  - Duke, centennial celebration of Normal College, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Duke University, Loyalty Fund, 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Duke University, 7 folders (Box 12)
  - Duke University, 3 folders (Box 13)
  - Education, 4 folders (Box 13)
  - Educational theory (Box 13)
  - English (Box 13)
  - Foreign Service, Mary Blair Smith (Box 13)
  - Good roads (Box 13)
  - Greensboro War Memorial (Box 13)
  - Greensboro Mission Society (Box 13)
  - Greensboro Public Schools, 7 folders (Box 14)
  - Greensboro Public Schools (Box 15)
  - Guilford College, Greensboro advisory board (Box 15)
  - Harrell, Bishop Costen, My Son (Box 15)
  - Historical miscellaneous materials, clippings (Box 15)
  - Holidays, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Hunter School (Box 15)
  - Integration, 3 folders (Box 15)
  - Integration, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Kiwanis Club, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Legislation, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Legislation (Box 17)
  - Libraries, 3 folders (Box 17)
  - Littlejohn's Church (Box 17)
  - Log schoolhouse preservation (Box 17)
  - Lowder, Hurley C., A Father's Letter to his Soldier Son (Box 17)
  - Methodist Church, 5 folders (Box 17)
  - Methodist Church, 9 folders (Box 18)
  - Methodist Church, 12 folders (Box 19)
  - Methodist Church (Box 20)
  - Miscellany, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Moral and spiritual values, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Mount Grove dedication (Box 20)
  - Nawakwa (Box 20)
  - North Carolina (Box 20)
  - North Carolina, Council of Churches (Box 20)
  - North Carolina, Council of Churches (Box 21)
  - North Carolina Education Association, 9 folders (Box 21)
  - North Carolina Education Association, 6 folders (Box 22)
  - North Carolina Public Schools, 3 folders (Box 22)
  - Older Boy's Conference, 2 folders (Box 22)
  - P.T.A. (Box 23)
  - Pfeiffer College, 4 folders (Box 23)
  - Phi Beta Kappa (Box 23)
  - Pictures, school buildings and personnel, "Shelby" (Box 23)
    [Contains photographic materials, most unidentified; not all are of Shelby schools.]
  - Poetry (Box 23)
  - Prohibition, Al Smith versus Herbert Hoover [elections of 1928] (Box 23)
  - Public versus private, Conant versus Polk (Box 23)
  - Readings (Box 23)
  - Reports (Box 23)
  - Rittenhouse, Montreal, Canada, the school library (Box 24)
  - Rutherford County (Box 24)
  - Rutherfordton-Spindale Schools (Box 24)
  - Schools - finance, 2 folders (Box 24)
  - Schools, 2 folders (Box 24)
  - Schools and Universities Committee (Box 24)
  - Schools - Shelby, North Carolina (Box 24)
  - unspecified (Box 24)
  - Segregation (Box 24)
  - Smith, Benjamin Lee, 2 folders (Box 24)
  - Smith, Benjamin Lee, 12 folders (Box 25)
    [Contains photographic materials]
  - Smith, Benjamin Lee, 4 folders (Box 26)
  - Southeastern Jurisdictional Council (Box 26)
  - State School Commission, finance (Box 26)
  - Superintendent's conference (Box 26)
  - Supervised study (Box 26)
  - Supplementary Election (Box 26)
  - Supervisor-Teacher (Box 27)
  - UNC (Box 27)
  - United States (Box 27)
  - George Washington, 2 folders (Box 27)
  - West Market Church (Box 27)
  - Woodrow Wilson Memorial (Box 27)
  - Youth Conservation (Box 27)
- Clippings Series, 1930-1961, 3 boxes
  Contains loose clippings chiefly regarding education and the school system in N.C.; the majority are from the Greensboro Daily News. Series also includes a number of issues of State School Facts, a bi-monthly publication from the state superintendent of public schools office. Organized in order received, roughly chronological.
  - 1930s-1950s, 7 folders (Box 27)
  - 1950s-1961, 13 folders (Box 28)
  - Clippings and quotations, 1 folder (Box 28)
  - State School Facts, 4 folders (Oversize-box 29)
- Printed Material Series, 1939-1961, 1 box
  Contains assorted materials which pertain to Benjamin Lee Smith's religious involvement and duties as superintendent of schools. In order as received.
  - Cities, promotional materials and Methodism (Box 30)
  - Magazine excerpts (Box 30)
  - Notes, 2 folders (Box 30)
  - Pamphlets and programs, 3 folders (Box 30)
- Speeches Series, 1916-1961, bulk 1930-1961, 1 box
  Contains speeches primarily authored by Benjamin Lee Smith, some of which deal with issues from his years as superintendent of schools. Also included is an essay submitted as an undergraduate to the Braxton Craven Contest. Miscellaneous folders contain assorted topics, the majority of which pertain to education, character values, morality, and inspirational themes on American life. Arranged in alphabetical order by topic.
  - Education, 4 folders (Box 31)
  - Horace Mann League (Box 31)
  - Integration (Box 31)
  - Libraries (Box 31)
  - Methodist Church (Box 31)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 31)
  - Notes, from other's speeches (Box 31)
  - Smith, Benjamin Lee, Public Education in the South Prior to 1860, Braxton Craven Contest (Box 31)
  - Thirtieth anniversary of the chartering of the Rutherfordton Kiwanis Club (Box 31)